ROBERT W. SCHUSTER, PHD

APPLIED BIOMECHANICS RESEARCHER, SPORT SCIENTIST

linkedin.com/in/robertwschuster | robertwschuster.github.io | Brisbane, AUS

PROFESSIONAL OVERVIEW

I am a naturally curious individual with a strong passion for investigating challenging questions and solving complex problems in the realm of biomechanics. My extensive experience encompasses the collection, processing, analysis and effective communication of biomechanical research data. I have consistently applied these skills across diverse fields related to human health and performance.

RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE

Griffith University | Gold Coast, AUS

10/2023 - present

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Lead interdisciplinary and industry-partnered research projects while supporting the writing of grant applications.

- Conduct research to provide athletic apparel brand with practical advice for the development of innovative athletic footwear.
- Collaborate with computer science researchers to explore the application of different machine learning and deep learning methods in the field of biomechanics.

The University of Queensland | Brisbane, AUS

07/2019 - 05/2023

Graduate Teaching Assistant & Senior Research Assistant

Supported a research project focused on predicting ground reaction forces from markerless 3D motion tracking during various activities. Developed and delivered course content for undergraduate students.

- Successfully leveraged skills in musculoskeletal modelling and supervised learning (linear mixed modelling) to deliver accurate results within tight deadlines.
- Applied R programming skills to create clear and insightful figures for interpretation, presentation and publication.

Australian Catholic University | Brisbane, AUS

05/2022 - 12/2022

Research Assistant

Provided programming expertise to expedite research projects related to human health and performance.

• Developed R Shiny apps and custom MATLAB routines for efficient data reduction, visualization and interpretation.

VALD | Brisbane, AUS

05/2022 - 07/2022

Industry Placement

Independently conducted proof-of-concept research for a novel application of a newly launched strength measurement device.

- Proactively gathered subjective client feedback and collected and analyzed research data to provide concise, practical recommendations regarding the integration of load cell and inertial measurement unit data.
- Seamlessly transitioned to programming in Python, leveraging prior programming skills.

Technical University of Munich | Munich, GER

05/2016 - 08/2018

Student Assistant & Scientific Staff Member

Conducted collaborative research with partners from leading national sports organizations, automotive, exercise equipment and clothing manufacturers. Developed and delivered content for undergraduate students.

- Gathered robust research data from high performance athletes, assembly line workers and the general population.
- Employed interpersonal skills to clearly and concisely communicate research concepts to diverse audiences.

EDUCATION

The University of Queensland | Brisbane, AUS

10/2018 - 03/2023

PhD in Biomechanics

- Collaborated with mechanical and electrical engineers to develop a custom force-instrumented measurement device.
- Proficiently applied unsupervised learning (PCA) and musculoskeletal modelling to study human locomotion.
- Contributed expertise to external research projects, providing actionable insight to shoe manufacturers.
- Nominated for the Dean's Award for outstanding contribution to the discipline.

SKILLS & INTERESTS

Methodologies: Proficient in 3D motion capture, force measurements, electromyography, inertial measurement units Computer: Adept at R, MATLAB, Python, OpenSim, Visual3D | Languages: German (native), English (near native), Spanish (fluent) Interests: rugby union, strength training, running, cooking, movies, reading (especially popular science)